A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Asia and Pacific, Program Budget and Administrative Files FA555
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Asia and Pacific, Program Budget and Administrative Files
1964-1981
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA555
5 Cubic Feet
4 Iron Mountain boxes and one half-size Hollinger document box
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Arranged in 2 series by file type.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
Contains program budgets and a small selection of administrative program files.
Biographical / Historical
Segment One: International Activities of the Ford Foundation: An Overview
The Foundation's aspiration to become a national and international philanthropy for the advancement of human welfare was first formally expressed in the seminal 1949 report of the Gaither Study Committee, >Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program (RAC Library, call letters 361.7 GAI ), which was commissioned by the Board of Trustees to chart the Foundation’s future. Foundation Trustees launched Ford’s international grantmaking activities in 1950 when they approved the committee’s report and its embrace of peace, democracy, and freedom. Since then, the Foundation has tackled these goals using a variety of strategies and responding to changing contexts, from the Cold War to the 1989 fall of the Berlin Wall and beyond.
Toward the Foundation’s aspiration‎al goal, "the establishment of peace", its international activities have comprised a wide range of conceptual approaches and focus areas. These include international affairs, international studies, international understanding, arms control and disarmament, international law, international economic concerns, and overseas development in nearly every region of the world. Three distinct periods emerge for the international grantmaking defined by external contextual changes and internal changes in Foundation leadership and structures: the expansion era of 1950-1965; the transition and restructuring years of 1966-1988; and the post-1989 shift away from Cold War dichotomies. During each of the distinct historical periods the consistent objectives were: 1) to ensure freedom and democracy in developed countries; 2) to foster education and international understanding in all countries; and 3) to contribute to the social, economic, and political development of less developed countries.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 2. Period Sketch - The Expansion Era 1950-1965
The Ford Foundation’s expansion era (1950-1965) began when the Gaither Study Committee Report placed “peace” as the area of top priority for the Foundation and set the Ford Foundation on a global course. Board Chair Henry Ford II writing in the 1951 Annual Report of the Foundation, identified “the danger of war” as the “the prime threat to human welfare today.” Under the leadership of the three Ford Foundation presidents in this period-- Paul Hoffman, H. Rowan Gaither and Henry Heald--and several key trustees, notably the two seriatim chairs, John J. McCloy and Julius A. Stratton, the Foundation programs were largely informed by the post-World War II desire to avoid nuclear war and promote greater understanding among the world’s peoples, strengthening of the United Nations, and enhancing both private and public American participation in world affairs. The strong board presence of university presidents and former leaders of postwar reconstruction efforts in Europe also helped to inform Ford’s approach to building the field of peace and international security in the United States and encouraged extensive overseas activities.
For example, the first three presidents of the expanded Foundation ranged from government and business leadership experience to academic and nonprofit: Paul Hoffman (at Ford, 1950-1953) ran the Marshall Plan in Europe; H. Rowan Gaither Staffer (1948-1953), President (1953-1956) and Trustee (1956-1958) had MIT and Rand experience; Henry Heald, former president, Illinois Institute of Technology and New York University, President (1956-1966). The trustees also ran the leadership gamut from government and nonprofits to academic: Trustee John J. McCloy (from 1953; chair, 1959-1965) was assistant Secretary of War during World War II and chairman of the Council on Foreign Relations; and Trustee Julius A. Stratton (Trustee from 1955; chair, 1966-1970) was president of MIT.
When Ford became an international foundation in 1950, it had a small staff and operated through separate funds. The expansive period in the 1950s and 1960s resulted in a large number of field offices, which increased Ford’s global footprint. Support focused on a mix of US university-based programs for research and training; think-tanks for policy-oriented meetings and policy research; and action projects specifically in less developed countries. The Foundation’s focus on peace, freedom, and democracy played out against the Cold War backdrop for scientific and military competition between the United States, the Soviet Union and China.
Under President Hoffman, the Foundation’s work was organized by the areas identified in the Gaither Committee Report: Area One, the Establishment of Peace; Area Two, The Strengthening of Democracy; Area Three, The Strengthening of the Economy; Area Four, Education in a Democratic Society; and Area Five, Individual Behavior and Human Relations.
Program differentiation began in the Gaither era. When he began in 1953, he introduced the following programs, with international work under nearly all of them: International Programs, Public Affairs Programs, Program in Economic Development and Administration (mainly U.S. based), Education Program, The TV-Radio Workshop, and Behavioral Sciences Program. In 1954, the Foundation gave prominence to the international work explicitly through changing the program names and separating international affairs and overseas development. The 1954 program names were: The Advancement of Education, Education for Democracy, Increasing Knowledge of Foreign Areas, Economic Development and Administration, the Behavioral Sciences, and Overseas Development. In 1955, Increasing Knowledge of Foreign Areas became Increasing International Understanding. In 1956, the last year of the Gaither presidency, the program roster read: Education in the United States, The Behavioral Sciences, Public Affairs, Hospital Aid (only in the U.S.), Economic Development and Administration, International Understanding, and Overseas Development. Names changed but the program focus often remained the same.
President Heald maintained the areas of international interest of Hoffman and Gaither. The International Affairs program housed the programs based in the United States, Europe and Japan, with a few activities linking American and developing countries institutions. The Overseas Training and Research Program took over the efforts to increase American understanding of international issues. From 1957-1959, an International Legal Studies program, run from New York, helped build law programs in developing countries. Starting in 1959, the Overseas Development program comprised all the regional and country offices. In fiscal year 1964, Heald convinced the trustees to add a new focus on population, with grants both in the United States and overseas.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 2. Period Summary - The Expansion Era 1950-1965
With the ever-increasing budget and trustee willingness to invade capital, presidents Hoffman, Gaither and Heald oversaw vast growth in the Foundation's international activities in the United States, other developed countries and developing countries. Activities crossed disciplines, institutions, and national boundaries, although few crossed intra-foundation boundaries. Under the three presidents, Foundation staff in various domestic and international offices from New York interacted with the regional and country offices headed by representatives. Usually in this period, however, these offices in fact worked more closely with local governments than with New York staff, reinforcing the commitment to locally led social and economic development in less-developed countries.
The shared values of this early period reflected as much the continuing competition between the Communist and capitalist worlds as the concerns about maintaining peace. The Cold War provided the contextual continuity for grantmaking on the core themes of increasing American understanding of the rest of the world, building and strengthening connections not only with European and Asian democracies but also with Eastern European countries, the Soviet Union, China, and Cuba.
- Program Budgets, 1965-1981; I
  - A&P General -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1967, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - India -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1967, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Indonesia -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1967 (Box 1)
  - Malaysia -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1967, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Pakistan -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1967, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Philippines -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1967, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - A&P General -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1968 (1 of 2), 1967 (Box 1)
  - A&P General -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1968 (2 of 2), 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - India -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1968, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Indonesia -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1968, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Malaysia -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1968, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Pakistan -- Program Budgets to 1968, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Pakistan -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1968, 1966-1969 (Box 1)
  - Philippines -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1968, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Thailand -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1968, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - A&P General (NY and East Asia) -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1969, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - India -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1969, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Indonesia -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1969, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Malaysia -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1969, 1968 (Box 1)
  - A&P General and New York -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1969, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - Pakistan -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1969, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Thailand -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1969, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - A&P New York and General -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1970, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Bangkok Office -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1970, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - East Asia -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1970, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - India -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1970, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Indonesia -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1970, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1970, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Thailand/Southeast Asia -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1970, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - A&P Resource Base Fiscal Year 1971, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Bangkok Office/Regional -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1971, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - India -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1971, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Indonesia -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1971, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - New York -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1971, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1971, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - Philippines -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1971, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Bangkok Office/Regional -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1972, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - East Asia -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1972, 1971 (Box 2)
  - India -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1972, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Indonesia -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1972, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - New York -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1972, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1972, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Philippines -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1972, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Bangladesh -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1973, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - India -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1973, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Indonesia -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1973, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1973, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Regional (Manila, Bangkok, and Malaysia) -- Program Budget Fiscal Year 1973, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - A&P General -- Program Budgets Fiscal Years 1974-1980 (Box 3)
  - A&P General -- Statistical Reports Fiscal Years 1970-1979 -- Grant Commitments by Subject and Cost Center; A&P Representatives Meeting (Jan 28-29, 1974) Program, 1973-1978 (Box 3)
  - Bangkok Office -- Program Budgets Fiscal Years 1974-1979, 1973-1979 (Box 3)
  - Dacca Office -- Program Budgets Fiscal Years 1974-1979, 1973-1978 (Box 3)
  - Islamabad Office -- Program Budgets Fiscal Years 1973-1978 (Box 3)
  - New Delhi Office -- Program Budgets Fiscal Years 1974-1983, 1973-1981 (Box 3)
  - Bangladesh -- Program Budgets Fiscal Years 1975-1981, 1974-1980 (Box 3)
  - India -- Program Budgets Fiscal Years 1974-1981, 1973-1981 (Box 4)
  - Indonesia -- Program Budgets (including background on region and Ford Foundation activities) Fiscal Years 1974-1981, 1965-1980 (Box 4)
  - Japan -- Program Budgets Fiscal Years 1976-1979 (Box 4)
  - New York -- Program Budgets Fiscal Years 1974-1981, 1973-1981 (Box 4)
  - Southeast Asia -- Program Budgets Fiscal Years 1974-1981 (Box 4)
- Administrative/General Files, 1964-1968, 1980; II
  - 64-423 Program Specialist and Consultant Services for Ford Foundation Program in South and Southeast Asia, 1964-1967 (Box 4)
  - Training Associates -- General -- South and Southeast Asia, 1964-1968 (Box 4)
  - Audit -- Tokyo, Japan, May 9-14, 1980 (Box 5)